Chapter 30. The pipe.
When Stub had departed, Ahab stood for a while, leaning over the bull works, and
then, as had been usual with him of late, calling a sailor of the watch, he
sent him below for his ivory stool, and also his pipe. Lighting his pipe at the
binnacle lamp, and planting the stool on the weather side of the deck, he sat and smoked.
In old Norse times, the thrones of the sea loving Danish kings were fabricated,
saith tradition, of the tusks of the narwhale. How could one look at Ahab
then, seated on that tripod of bones, without bethinking him of the royalty it
symbolized? For a con of the plank and a king of the sea, and a great lord of
Leviathans was Ahab.
Some moments passed during which the thick vapor came from his mouth in quick
and constant puffs which blew back again into his face. How now? He saliloquised
at last, withdrawing the tube. This smoking no longer soothes. Oh, my pipe.
Hard must it go with me if thy charm be gone. Here have I been unconsciously
toiling, not pleasuring. I and ignorantly smoking to windward all the
while to windward and with such nervous whiffs as if like the dying whale my
final jets were the strongest and fullest of trouble. What business have I
with this pipe? This thing that is meant for sereness to send up mild white
vapors among mild white hairs, not among torn iron gray locks like mine. I'll smoke no more.
He tossed the still lighted pipe into the sea. The fire hissed in the waves
the same instant the ship shot by the bubble the sinking pipe made. With
slouched hat, Ahab lurchingly paced the planks.